NETWORK TECHNICIAN - SYSTEMS ARCHITECTURE

Professional Summary

Mission oriented professional with over nineteen years of leadership and management experience in operations, logistics, and nine years specifically in information technology. Provide exemplary analysis, documentation, and plan development of all assigned projects and programs. Well-rounded education, job diversity, and work experience allows me the ability to apply creative thinking to the decision making process to support missions and requirements.

Skills

- Remote access support
- Systems analysis
- LAN and WAN expertise
- Superb interpersonal skills
- Remote access support
- · Systems analysis
- · Wireless Access Point
- LAN and WAN expertise
- Superb interpersonal skills

Work History

Network Technician - Systems Architecture , 06/2012 to Current Altamira – Dayton , OH

- Provide analysis, documentation, recommendations, and implementation of network equipment and infrastructure upgrades based on
 experience, technical engineering and problem solving skills, and Best Business Practices to bring the district to DOD and commercial IT
 standards.
- Provide Subject Matter Expertise to recommend and establish architectural priorities for a complex 5-year IT Capitalization investment project.
- The project consists of multiple tasks which includes Inside/Outside Plant Rewire planning, Network Refresh design, IP Telephony upgrade planning, CSSVSAT installation, and District wide Wi-Fi implementation.
- Plan, Prepare, Design, and Implement network refresh project consisting of headquarters and 12 field sites in Washington, Idaho, and Montana.
- The Network Refresh install includes 14 Cisco Routers, 8 Voice Gateways, 5508 Wireless Controller, 148 Cisco 3750x switches, 75 Wireless Access Points, and 57 Conference Stations.
- Initial budgeting for project at around \$1.1 million.
- Effective oral and written communications on the Network Refresh and IT Capitalization projects to the IT Chief and Operations Branch
 Officer, and persuade and recommend to Site Project Managers the requirements, tasks, and costs of the Refresh and Capitalization plans.
- Established detailed and complete district wide documentation of the network topology to a standard model when there were no existing or adequate documentation.
- Collaborated with a team to develop an in-depth IT technical documentation for each site for the IT Chief and Operations Officer as well as Site Project Managers for visibility of equipment, capability, and solutions for issues at each site.
- Assist and provide customer service on Break/fix issues in network, voice, and infrastructure outages.
- Upgraded and expanded network systems and their components.
- Designed and implemented networks in collaboration with project engineers.

Network Engineer , 01/2007 to 01/2012

St Therese Home Of New Hope â€" Robbinsdale, MN

- Manage routers, switches, UPS, and WAAS appliances state-wide at 44 Remote Branch Sites and 4 Campus sites.
- Independently established WAN-LAN Standard Operating Procedures which dealt with Network Outages, Wireless MAN
 troubleshooting, Network failover management, Router/ Switch maintenance, MDF/IDF installation, WAAS Server Management, UPS
 Management, and site visit tasks.
- Implemented and deployed UPS management to 150 UPS devices state-wide in 44 branch sites and 4 campuses.
- Lead and or participate in team projects and presentations dealing with lifecycle upgrades, bandwidth management, VOIP implementation,
 UPS Installation and Management, Kiosk Installation, and Network Access Control.
- Plan, coordinate, and develop budgeting to support infrastructure upgrades.
- Effectively communicate to the IT Branch Manager, CIO, Commanders, and Full-time staff on network and specific IT activities in the domain.
- Developed requirements for 3 campus sites for network infrastructure upgrade of \$360,000. Equipment consisted of routers, switches, and VOIP telephony.
- Developed and implemented the headquarters network infrastructure upgrade requirement projected at \$59,000.
- Managed and implemented statewide site server consolidation project, file server, and print services consolidation with a triennial cost savings of \$87,000 in equipment lifecycle and manpower.
- On my own initiative, consolidated documentation and resources for deployment, implementation, and maintenance of 270 kiosk systems state-wide when there were no project officer assigned.
- Built server systems and installed into racks.
- Reviewed logs for all networking devices for unresolved abnormalities and problems.
- Troubleshot and maintained all networking devices and infrastructure across the enterprise including switches, routers and firewalls.
- Communicated with vendors to resolve network outages and periods of reduced performance.
- Kept up-to-date on new developments in computer and network vulnerabilities, data hiding and encryption.
- Documented all server and network problems and other unusual events in detail.

- Upgraded and expanded network systems and their components.
- Completed remote repairs involving software solutions and hardware repairs.

Information Technology Specialist , 01/2005 to 01/2006 Chenega Corporation â \in Philadelphia , PA

Manage network devices in my area of responsibility

Training and Mobilization Analyst , 01/1998 to 01/2005 City Of San Antonio , Tx \hat{a} E" San Antonio , TX

- Develop policies, processes, procedures, and budget requirements for administration, fiscal, operations, training, and logistics for units
 conducting domestic and overseas training using knowledge and skills acquired from previous positions.
- Formulate, plan training and evaluation activities to monitor unit compliance with training policies, regulations and directives.
- Plan activities, policies, processes and program requirements for units to successfully accomplish readiness goals.
- Develop, update, and validate budget estimates up to \$5 million for administration, fiscal, operations, training, and logistics for units
 conducting domestic training and overseas deployment for combat operations.
- Developed a detailed spreadsheet annotating costs and expenditures for multiple deployments that were used as a model for other states to use as a baseline document.

Brigade Maintenance Officer, 01/1997 to 01/2001

41st Separate Infantry Brigade, Oregon Army National Guard –City , STATE

- Responsible for maintenance management of 865 pieces of rolling stock and 48 sets of power generation equipment worth over \$8 million.
- Coordinates with Direct Support, Material Management Center and Installation representatives to enhance unit readiness.
- Plan and provide training to 40 maintenance personnel in a variety of maintenance occupational specialties.
- Established and developed brigade and company level maintenance Standard Operating Procedures.
- Effectively communicate Brigade Maintenance Operations to logistics and operational staffs to ensure a high readiness state equipment requiring maintenance.
- Increased maintenance personnel proficiency on automation systems in maintaining 80% or better equipment availability.

Project Manager, 01/1995 to 01/1998

41 Separate Infantry Brigade, Oregon Army National Guard â€" City, STATE

- Managed 7 operations and logistics supervisors supporting Army Guard/Reserve/Active Duty units from 22 states, US Air Force, and US Marine Corps units and commands assigned to the project.
- Plan, establish, validate, and request resource requirements approximately \$1.5 million in primary, incidental, and implied training costs for administration, fiscal, operations, training, and logistics for units conducting training.
- Planned, directed, and coordinated activities to insure that goals and objectives specified for the project are accomplished in accordance with prescribe policies, processes, priorities, time limitations, and funding conditions.
- Provide effective communication between assigned units by correspondence, reports and briefings for guidance, planning, programming, and develop solutions to problems and directs implementation.

Training Officer, 01/1993 to 01/1994

103d Troop Command, Hawaii Army National Guard â€" City, STATE

- Developed long and short range planning guidance for 400 soldiers with 8 subordinate commands.
- Focus of work was on training, readiness, and physical security.
- Prepared and conducted staff meetings for the command.
- Monitored program budget disbursement up to \$800,000 to subordinate commands and managed school training funds for soldiers.
- Effectively communicate Brigade Operations and Training status to commanders, staffs and subordinate units for guidance, planning, programming, budgeting, and develop solutions to problems and direct implementation.

Education

Bachelor of Arts: University of Hawaii - City, State

Music

Associate: Science, Administration of Justice, Honolulu Community College - City, State

Science, Administration of Justice

Diploma: W.R. Farrington High School - City, State

Microsoft Certified System Engineer+ Messaging: MCP ID 2354747 CompTIA Security+ Certified Professional: COMP10532820 CompTIA Network+ Certified Professional: COMP10532820 CISCO Certified Network Associate-Voice: CSCO11286671 CISCO Certified Network Associate-Security: CSCO11286671 CISCO Certified Network Associate: CSCO11286671:

Air Force, Army, automation, Backup, budgeting, budget, CISCO Certified Network Associate, Cisco, Cisco Routers, oral, hardware, Controller, customer service, documentation, Engineer, Focus, funds, Gateways, Information Technology, IP, ISA, LAN, leadership, logistics, meetings, Messaging, Access, MCP, Microsoft Certified, Microsoft Exchange Server, Outlook, Migration, network printers, network servers, Network, personnel, policies, presentations, printer, printers, problem solving skills, processes, programming, requirement, Router, routers,

servers, site server, spreadsheet, switches, Switch, technical documentation, Telephony, troubleshooting, upgrades, upgrade, VOIP, WAN, written communications	
written communications	